A Guide to the William Moffett Papers, 1937-1984
Augusta County Historical Society
Augusta County Historical Society
William Moffett Papers, 1937-1984
Augusta County Historical Society
2021.0026
10 boxes, 4 ft., 8.5 in.
William Stuart Moffett, Jr.
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Files and books from William Moffett's law practice in Staunton, Virginia, were in storage at the Augusta County Courthouse. The Courthouse donated the collection to the Augusta County Historical Society.
Biographical/Historical Note
Files and books from William Moffett's law practice in Staunton, Virginia, were in storage at the Augusta County Courthouse. The Courthouse donated the collection to the Augusta County Historical Society.
William Stuart Moffett, Jr., was born September 6, 1910, at Annandale Farm in Augusta County, Virginia. He was the son of Fannie Bailie and state Senator William Stuart Moffett, Sr. He married Cornelia Taylor Quarles on June 24, 1937.
He died at his home, on August 20, 2002, and is buried in Thornrose Cemetery, Staunton, Virginia.
William Moffett graduated from Robert E. Lee High School in Staunton and from Virginia Polytechnic Institute with a B.S. degree in Industrial Engineering. While at VPI, he was captain of his company and president of the Corps of Cadets. He graduated from the University of Virginia Law School in 1936 and set up a law practice in Staunton the same year. From 1942 to 1946 he served in the U.S. Army's Judge Advocate General Corps, after which he returned to private practice in Staunton. His law office was in the Echols Building.
He was appointed Judge of the 18th Judicial Circuit Court on April 1, 1955, and served the counties of Augusta, Highland, and Rockbridge, including the cities of Staunton, Lexington, and Buena Vista for more than 28 years until his retirement in 1984.
Judge Moffett served on various boards and commissions, including the Augusta County Tuberculosis Association, Virginia Tech Board of Visitors, Board of the National Valley Bank, and the Board of People's Bank of Stuarts Draft. He was a member of the Staunton Rotary Club, the Virginia Tech William Preston Society, a Charter member and past president of the Hugh B. Sproul Tent of Circus Saints and Sinners, and was a lifelong member of Tinkling Spring Presbyterian Church where he served as a chairman of the Board of Deacons.
Scope and Content
The files and books were in cardboard boxes. Dividers in the boxes indicated they were originally filed in alphabetical order. The alphabetical arrangement has, therefore, been maintained.
The collection is incomplete. There are no clients with last names beginning with A, I, J, M, N, O, Q, R, U, X, and Z, only one file with a name beginning with H, one with P, one with B (Bank of Craigsville), and two files with names beginning with S.
Some of the files contain, in addition to documents for the client whose name appears on the file, items apparently related to different clients. The documents may have been misfiled or mixed up when the files were transferred to the historical society. The files in this collection have been left as they were received, with no attempt to correct possible misfilings.
The contents of the files represent typical types of cases handled by a mid-20th century small town law practice. The majority are wills, divorces, adoptions, estates, and deeds drawn up for individual clients. Mr. Moffett also represented several churches, some local companies, associations, and cooperatives. They range in date from approximately 1946 to 1954.
In addition to the client files, there are 9 loose canceled checks in an envelope, related to the estate of A.N. Dull, of which Moffett was the executor.
There are loose ledger pages listing accounts of individual clients. There are pages from a legal pad with monthly trial balances of accounts.
Two boxes of books are account and check ledgers from Moffett's law practice. The ledgers date from 1937 to 1954 and list debits and credits. The writing is hard to read. Most of the entries are fees for legal services provided, and office expenses. Some entries record cash payments from one person, which Moffett's office then sends as a check to a second person.
There are 17 ledgers with check stubs, listing payments for costs of running the office, such as rent, social security, purchases of office supplies, utility bills, payments to sheriffs for summonses, notary fees, etc. There are salary payments to Emma H. Bishop, who in 1950 received $130 monthly.
There's a bank book from Staunton National Bank with 9 pages filled in. The entries go from 1949 to 1955 and are records of deposits with no notes. The rest of the book is blank.
One large ledger is labeled "Transfer Ledger Sheets from 1946 - Wm. S. Moffett, Jr., Attorney." Some pages appear to be client accounts; others are "general expenses."
There's a book, Almanac for Business Management, published in 1946.
Index Terms
Persons:
Moffett, William Stuart, Jr.
Subjects:
Lawyers - Virginia - Staunton
Contents List
- Bank of Craigsville (Box-folder 1-1)
- J.E. Cale (Box-folder 1-2)
- Waddell C. Calhoun (Box-folder 1-3)
- J.S. Callison (Box-folder 1-4)
- John Walker Callison (Box-folder 1-5)
- Fred N. Campbell (Box-folder 1-6)
- J.S. Carrier Estate (Box-folder 1-7)
- B.G. Cash (Box-folder 1-8)
- Charlie L. Cash (Box-folder 1-9)
- Clyde Franklin Cash (Box-folder 1-10)
- Arthur R. Cason (Box-folder 1-11)
- Ceda-Cene Products Inc. (Box-folder 1-12 to 1-15)
- DeWitt Chandler estate (Box-folder 1-16)
- T.A. Chandler vs Powell et als (Box-folder 1-17)
- Mrs. Raymond Chaplin (Box-folder 1-18)
- Checkbook (Box-folder 1-19)
- Luther E. Childress (Box-folder 1-20)
- Walter Chilton (Box-folder 2-21)
- Civil and Police Justice Court (Box-folder 2-22)
- Civil Defense (Box-folder 2-23)
- Harry T. Clark (Box-folder 2-24)
- Houston A. Clark (Box-folder 2-25)
- James Robert Clark (Box-folder 2-26)
- Burnett S. Clatterbaugh (Box-folder 2-27)
- Grace Kuhn Clatterbaugh (Box-folder 2-28)
- George E. Clements (Box-folder 2-29)
- C.E. Clemmer (Box-folder 2-30)
- Irvine G. Cline (Box-folder 2-31)
- Joseph Minor Cline (Box-folder 2-32)
- Kermit Russell Cline (Box-folder 2-33)
- Mrs. Minnie Belle Cline (Box-folder 2-34)
- P.F. Cline Estate (Box-folder 2-35)
- Mrs. Ruth Diamond Clough (Box-folder 2-36)
- Frank M. Coffey (Box-folder 2-37)
- Nellie Woodzell Coffey (Box-folder 2-38)
- Virgil L. Coffey (Box-folder 2-39)
- Roy Y. Coffman, executor, estate of Elizabeth C. Coffman (Box-folder 2-40)
- Mrs. Alice V. Coleman (J.A. Coleman estate) (Box-folder 2-41 to 2-43)
- Ora C. Collins & others (Box-folder 3-44)
- Mrs. Virginia Madeline Colvin (Box-folder 3-45)
- Virginia F. Conner estate (Box-folder 3-46)
- Consolidated Hair Goods Co. (Box-folder 3-47)
- Florence Mae Reece Cornett (Box-folder 3-48)
- Ernest B. Craun (Box-folder 3-49)
- Mrs. Emma L. Crawford, admix, John W. Carpenter estate (Box-folder 3-50)
- C.M. Crummett (Box-folder 3-51)
- A.J. Cullen (Box-folder 3-52)
- Lee A. Cupp (Box-folder 3-53)
- James A. Curd (Box-folder 3-54)
- Walter S. Daggy (Box-folder 3-55)
- Margaret T. Daniel (Box-folder 3-56)
- Carrie & Henry Darcus (Box-folder 3-57)
- Mr. & Mrs. L.W. Davis (Box-folder 3-58)
- L. Walter Davis (Box-folder 3-59)
- Dean & Parrish (Box-folder 3-60)
- Mrs. Cora E. Dedrick (Box-folder 3-61)
- Deeds and contracts (miscellaneous) (Box-folder 3-62 to 3-66)
- Henry C. DeJarnette (Box-folder 4-67)
- J.C. Dell, Jr. (Box-folder 4-68)
- Mrs. Drucilla E. Demastus (Box-folder 4-69)
- W.E.B. Dennison (Box-folder 4-70)
- B.M. DePriest (Box-folder 4-71)
- Clarence Desper (Box-folder 4-72)
- Clarence H. Desper estate - Madeline R. Desper (Box-folder 4-73)
- S.W. Desper (Box-folder 4-74)
- Larry D. DeVenny (Box-folder 4-75)
- Harry B. Dice (Box-folder 4-76)
- Marguerite R. Dickerson (Box-folder 4-77)
- T.C. Dickerson, Jr. (Box-folder 4-78 to 4-79)
- A.J.S. Diehl estate (Box-folder 4-80)
- William Garnet Dill (Box-folder 4-81)
- Mrs. Ella Dodd (Box-folder 4-82)
- Mrs. Pearl M. Dodge (Box-folder 4-83)
- Isaac Donner (Box-folder 4-84)
- Meredith C. Dortch (Box-folder 4-85)
- D.B. Driver (Box-folder 4-86)
- Henry J. Drummond (Box-folder 4-87)
- Dennis W. Dull, admin. W.H. Dull (Box-folder 4-88)
- W.E. Dull estate (Box-folder 5-89)
- Everett Lesley Dunaway (Box-folder 5-90)
- Reba C. Dunlap (Box-folder 5-91)
- E.I duPont de Nemours & Company (Box-folder 5-92)
- Carl E. Durham (Box-folder 5-93)
- Felix B. Dutton estate (Box-folder 5-94)
- Harry D. Dyer (Box-folder 5-95)
- Hunter Eugene Earhart (Box-folder 5-96)
- Early Dawn Cooperative Dairy, Inc. (Box-folder 5-97)
- William H. East (Box-folder 5-98)
- D.H. Eavers estate, Ira W. Eavers, Adm. (Box-folder 5-99)
- William B. Edwards (Box-folder 5-100)
- James W. Elick (Box-folder 5-101)
- Mrs. Georgia J. Ellis (Box-folder 5-102)
- O.R. Engleman (Engleman Hardware Co.) (Box-folder 5-103)
- Erwin Motor Company, Inc. (Box-folder 5-104)
- Mary Bryant Eutsler (Box-folder 5-105)
- Charles B. Evans (Box-folder 5-106)
- Robert T. Evans (Box-folder 5-107)
- Walter L. Evans estate (Box-folder 5-108)
- Mrs. Anna Louise Wright Faison (Box-folder 5-109)
- Ellis E. Fauber (Box-folder 5-110)
- James Fauber (Box-folder 5-111)
- Charles M. Fielder (Box-folder 5-112)
- Finley Memorial Presbyterian Church (Box-folder 5-113)
- John Franklin Fisher (Box-folder 5-114)
- Katherine Isabelle Painter Fisher (Box-folder 5-115)
- Mrs. Lilly Mary Fisher (Box-folder 5-116 to 5-117)
- Fishersville Methodist Church (Box-folder 6-118)
- B.G. Fitzgerald, Jr. (Box-folder 6-119)
- Mrs. Edna Fitzgerald (Box-folder 6-120)
- John Franklin Fitzgerald & others, estate of Isaac Fitzgerald (Box-folder 6-121)
- Manley L. Fitzgerald (Box-folder 6-122)
- Robert Frank Fitzgerald (Box-folder 6-123)
- Roy Austin Fitzgerald, incompetent (Box-folder 6-124)
- Samuel F. Fitzgerald (Box-folder 6-125 to 6-126)
- John H. Flavin (Box-folder 6-127)
- O.C. Flory (Box-folder 6-128)
- C.S. Fogle (Box-folder 6-129)
- James W. Forbes v. Edward M. VanFossen (Box-folder 6-130)
- John K. Forrer (Box-folder 6-131 to 6-132)
- Waide H. Frank, estate of G.A. Frank (Box-folder 6-133)
- Millard C. Fridley (Box-folder 6-134)
- Fruit Growers Cooperative Corporation, Crozet, Virginia (Box-folder 6-135 to 6-136)
- William Fuqua (Box-folder 6-137)
- Charles S. Gaw, guardian of Anne Gaw (Box-folder 7-138)
- F.M. Gayhart (Box-folder 7-139)
- Vivian D. Gibson, estate of Beverley V. Gibson (Box-folder 7-140)
- Miss Blanche Gilbert (Box-folder 7-141)
- A.C. Gilkeson (Box-folder 7-142)
- A. Crawford Gilkeson, executor, Georgie B. Harbeson, deceased (Box-folder 7-143)
- G.M. Gilkeson, guardian of Mary Hope Howe (Box-folder 7-144)
- Mrs. Louise Doniphan Gilkeson (Box-folder 7-145 to 7-146)
- Mrs. Dorothy Ballew Glenn (Box-folder 7-147)
- Boyd J. Glock (Box-folder 7-148)
- Samuel W. Glover (Box-folder 7-149)
- David E. Gochenour (Box-folder 7-150)
- Mrs. Fannie H. Gochenour, guardian of Frances Lee Hughes (Box-folder 7-151)
- Mr. William B. Goodloe (Box-folder 7-152)
- Grooms v Grooms, et als (Box-folder 7-153 to 7-154)
- George M. Grove estate (Box-folder 8-155 to 8-156)
- Herman L. Gwin (Box-folder 8-157)
- Isabelle Lumsden Hevener (Box-folder 8-158)
- John T. Key (Box-folder 8-159)
- Charles B. Kilburn (Box-folder 8-160)
- King’s Daughters Hospital (Box-folder 8-161)
- Milton N. Kinsinger (Box-folder 8-162)
- A.J. Kiracofe (Box-folder 8-163)
- C.W. Kiracofe estate, Annie M. Kiracofe executrix (Box-folder 8-164)
- L.S. Kiracofe estate (Box-folder 8-165)
- Clark C. Kirby (Box-folder 8-166)
- Clark C. Kirby estate (Box-folder 8-167 to 8-169)
- Mrs. Sue Kirby (Box-folder 8-170)
- Frances M. Kreitzer (Box-folder 8-171)
- Mary Lou Kunkel (Box-folder 8-172)
- Ray R. Landes (Box-folder 8-173)
- Dr. Frank A. Lasley, Sr. (Box-folder 8-174)
- Lawyers Title Insurance (Box-folder 8-175)
- Lawyer’s Weekly Letter (Box-folder 9-176 to 9-177)
- William B. Lee (Box-folder 9-178)
- W.H. Lessley (Box-folder 9-179)
- Trustees of Lexington Presbytery c/o Rev. W.C. Jamison (Box-folder 9-180)
- Mrs. Alice B. Lightner (Box-folder 9-181)
- Robert A. Lightner (Box-folder 9-182)
- Little River Hunt Club (Box-folder 9-183)
- J.E. Lotts estate (Box-folder 9-184)
- L.W.H. Peyton (Box-folder 9-185)
- Stuarts Draft Volunteer Fire Company (Box-folder 9-186)
- Mary F. Taylor (Box-folder 9-187 to 9-188)
- Mrs. Karl C. Teufel (Box-folder 9-189)
- W.H. Tewalt (Box-folder 9-190)
- Everett W. Thomas (Box-folder 9-191)
- Harry L. Thomas (Box-folder 9-192)
- Mrs. Willa S. Thomas (Box-folder 9-193)
- Mr. William W. Thomas (Box-folder 9-194)
- Mrs. Edna P. Thompson (Box-folder 9-195)
- Imogene Thompson (Box-folder 9-196)
- James E. Thornton (Box-folder 9-197 to 9-198)
- David A. Tinsley (re property owned by M.E. Green estate) (Box-folder 9-199)
- Houston I. Todd (Box-folder 9-200)
- Dr. Howard E. Topping (Box-folder 9-201)
- Mrs. Ephra V. Townley (Box-folder 9-202)
- Joseph Baxter Trimble estate (Box-folder 10-203 to 10-206)
- Mrs. W.B. Trimble (Box-folder 10-207)
- Tuberculosis Association (Box-folder 10-208)
- Eugene Conway Tuttle (Box-folder 10-209)
- James B.Tuttle (Box-folder 10-210)
- John B. Tuttle (Box-folder 10-211)
- Valley Trading Corporation (Box-folder 10-212)
- Wallace B. Varner (Box-folder 10-213)
- George B. Venable, Jr. (Box-folder 10-214)
- Mary Ellen Vest, guardian of Arthur Vest (Box-folder 10-215)
- VFW Post, Stuarts Draft (Box-folder 10-216)
- Mrs. Gary Vinson (Box-folder 10-217)
- L.A. Vint (Box-folder 10-218)
- Wade & Miller vs Sheffer (Box-folder 10-219)
- James A. Wade (Box-folder 10-220)
- H. Wallace (Box-folder 10-221)
- N.C. Waller (Box-folder 11-222)
- Grady B. Ware (Box-folder 11-223)
- Virginia Brown Ware (Box-folder 11-224)
- Fannie Mae Becks Watts (Box-folder 11-225)
- Mrs. Vallie S. Weaver (Box-folder 11-226)
- Mrs. Cecil H. Weller (Box-folder 11-227)
- Warren Newton Wescott (Box-folder 11-228)
- John D. White (Box-folder 11-229 to 11-230)
- Lillie Ellen White (Box-folder 11-231)
- W.H. Wright (Box-folder 11-232)
- Mrs. R.H. Young, estate of R.H. Young (Box-folder 11-233)
- Mr. R.R. Yount (Box-folder 11-234)
- Accounts (monthly trial balances) (Box-folder 11-235)
- Loose pages from account ledgers & checks (Box-folder 11-236)
- (Box 12)
  - Staunton National Bank, account of Wm. S. Moffett, Jr., May 11, 1949-June 9, 1955
  - Expense journal, August 15, 1937
  - Expense journal, February 1938
  - Expense journal, October 1938
  - Expense journal, October 1939
  - Expense journal, October 1940
  - Expense journal, August 1941
  - Expense journal, August 1942
  - Expense journal, fall 1946
  - Checkbook, November 12, 1936-May 31, 1938
  - Checkbook, June 1, 1938-May 24, 1939
  - Checkbook, May 24, 1939-December 4, 1939
  - Checkbook, December 11, 1939-June 21, 1940
  - Checkbook, June 28, 1940-December 11, 1940
  - Checkbook, December 12, 1940-May 29, 1941
  - Checkbook, National Valley Bank, July 17, 1939-October 21, 1942
  - Checkbook, May 31, 1941-October 31, 1941
  - Checkbook, November 1, 1941-May 6, 1942
  - Checkbook, May 6, 1942-October 24, 1942
  - Checkbook, January 3, 1947-October 7, 1947
  - Checkbook, October 29, 1942-January 3, 1947
  - Checkbook, October 10, 1947-June 22, 1948
  - Checkbook, June 25, 1948-September 24, 1948
  - Checkbook, September 29, 1948-March 28, 1959
  - Checkbook, March 31, 1950-May 31, 1951
  - Checkbook, June 1, 1951-September 11, 1952
  - Checkbook, Staunton National Bank, September 11, 1952-March 30, 1954
- (Box 13)
  - Ledger #2, October 1, 1947
  - Ledger #3, October 1, 1949
  - Ledger #4, July 3, 1951
  - Ledger #5, April 1, 1953
  - Transfer ledger sheets from 1946
  - Almanac for Business Management (NY: Prentice-Hall, 1946)